hey everyone today we're going to
learn about different ways that I
script and prep scripts for narration for
voiceovers and other things like that now
most of what I do is the voiceovers for these
tutorial videos or for pluralsights or for
udemy and things like that but I'm going to
share some of my lessons learned that will
hopefully help you if you have to do the same
thing so let's go ahead and get started [Music]
all right welcome back my name is Jeff bat and
if you haven't checked out my website already
go ahead and check out my website here you can
learn about all things learning development and
you can check out all previous blog posts on
tips and tricks on articulate storyline Adobe
captivates how to do AR as well as just tips and
tricks for production all of the different blog
posts that I've made in the last two years are
here you can also download templates templates
and articulate storyline and X API and if you're
new to any of these tools you can check out full
courses everything from A to Z on articulate
storyline 360 Adobe Captivate xapi fundamentals
Camtasia articulate rice custom scorm and HTML5
video now like I mentioned before I have done a
lot of narration mostly for like pluralsights
or udemy and or for different courses as well
there's a couple different things to keep in mind
as I've created scripts and a couple different
tips and tricks that I've learned and throughout
the years that I wanted to share with you every
voiceover artist has their own I mean I wouldn't
even consider myself a voice over artist I've just
done a lot of narration stuff everyone has their
own process everyone has their own prep uh you
know you know prepping and making sure they're
ready to go with their voice so I don't want to
say that this is the best way but this is just
the ways that I have done where I have learned
to help me in my voice overs and my scripting as
well so I just wanted to make sure that that's
clear because I know there are some people that
are like no you shouldn't do this no you shouldn't
do that I I don't think it's that black and white
I think it's you know there's ways that work for
people there's ways that don't work for people
it just depends on what works for you so keep
that in mind so I'm going to go ahead and pull
up my slides here and in the scripting and prep
there's a couple things to keep in mind this is
the first question that I get a lot do you script
should you script or should you not script for my
videos for my blog posts I don't script I actually
just have some bullet points I I think of a topic
and I write down a couple of bullet points that I
want to cover and then I go from there I've just
done so many in the past two years I've done so
many of these blog posts that it's just easier
for me not to script I'll just be honest I am
not a writer I am not I am more a developer than
anything else but I am not a writer it's hard for
me to sit down and write out exactly what I'm
going to say and one of the other reasons why
I I don't script a lot is because a lot of the
times with my scripting it will sound robotic
unless I script it in a certain way which I'll
talk to you about in a second here but that's
one of the reasons why I don't script especially
with on camera videos is because I want them to
make I want to make them sound more fluid and more
energized as well but that's up to you so if if
scripting works for you great if you feel more
comfortable with scripting great use scripting
and hopefully these tips and tricks for the times
that I have scripted for like pluralsights and
udemy and other things like that these tips and
tricks have helped me out with scripting so we're
going to talk about scripting or unscripting we're
going to talk about scripting with markup and
we're going to talk about lists some of the other
ways that I've already mentioned and some of the
tips and tricks for that so first of all let's
talk about unscripted one of the key things for
unscripted is knowledge if you know the tool if
you know whatever you're going to be talking about
it then it comes a whole lot easier and so that's
one of the reasons why I could go into articulate
storyline and show you how to create a tabs
interaction and just you know add a few bullet
points but not have to script out everything
because I've taught it so much and I've talked
about it so much that it just flows a lot better
the tip is for you is to learn your content if
you're not going to script make sure you know your
content you've practiced just giving the session
or giving presenting the knowledge to somebody or
something like that or just pull up your iPhone
and record it this helps you practice and this
this helps you gain that knowledge especially
sharing the knowledge and sharing what others need
to know about it and it really comes with practice
it comes with you just getting it out and doing
it and presenting it several different times post
YouTube videos helps you practice what you're
talking about as well so this is an example and
I'm going to pull this up real quick of a not
marked up script and so this one I believe it
is a trailer for my pluralsight course and so they
have very specific things on pluralsight that they
want you to talk about inside kind of reach here
this is what I started out with my script here
now if I'm going in and I'm reading this there's a
couple things that don't really speak to me right
here and it makes a little bit harder for me to
read possibly with just my reading disability it
just makes it harder for it to sound natural here
I'm going to talk a little bit about scripting so
even if I wasn't to mark it up or anything like
that the first recommendation that I would do is
to take it line by line so this means coming into
my script here and going down and separating out
each line each thought here to make sure that it's
separated and it's clear so now I can go in and if
I'm not on camera I could go in and just practice
this a couple times hi everyone my name is Jeff
Batten welcome to my course on JavaScript arrays
and collections practice that a few times so once
you practice it then you can hit record and then
you could just say that line now you can cut out
in post edit you can cut out spaces between these
lines so even though you're pausing and going to
the next line you can cut out that space so it
sounds natural that's one of the benefits of
recording is you can cut out all your mistakes and
by scripting though I do find that I I tend not to
say uh and um so that is a benefit of scripting
and it is more concise and more clear so I'm not
saying don't script there are some clear benefits
to scripting and these are some of the tips and
tricks that I've learned when I cut it out line
by line it's easy for me to focus on on one line
at a time practice it a couple times hit record
and such the other thing that you can do is you
can mark up your script now there are a couple
different ways to mark up your scripts and you
can see over on the right hand side this allows
me to visually actually get used to a couple of
different things so I'm going to pull up that
same script and you'll notice here hi everyone
my name is Jeff bat and welcome you'll notice
a couple different tips and tricks here which
we'll cover what all of these means the different
color the italicized in certain areas the orange
in certain areas as well the pauses the two the
three and so forth I'm going to cover all of that
especially the OST as well what does all of this
mean if you're new to reading the narration even
having all of these kind of markups may you know
take a little getting used to but once you've done
a few of them by seeing those markups visually it
triggers how you need to read certain areas let's
go ahead and go into what some of those markups
mean so the first thing is color when you have
different colors that emphasize different areas
you can talk about those colors in certain ways
and the first one is names what I do is usually go
Mark anybody's name in blue or any name of like a
software in blue or any name of like for example
if I was teaching about JavaScript I would talk
about JavaScript I would Mark that in blue as well
the next thing is questions because I like to make
sure that I have the inflections of questions when
I'm going into the question because sometimes I'll
read it maybe it's just me but sometimes I'll read
it not as a question and realize at the end of the
question that it was a question so I like to Mark
those out as purple so when I first start reading
the sentence it will be clearly a question now if
I come back into here I'm going to scroll up and
you'll notice right here what I do and possibly
this could come from me learning Spanish as
well is I add a upside down question mark at the
beginning and then I have it as purple you don't
have to do that but that's at the very beginning
lets me know that it's a question so I can make
sure that I do the inflections correctly or even
pause for a second before I do the question so
that is one way that I mark up is I do the blue
for names and very important things and then I
do the purple for questions and then I do red
for screen movements if I know there's going
to be a specific time of type of screen movement
especially if I'm doing narration separate from
the actual screen recording I will Mark the
the movements in red and that way I know that
the camera as I'm talking about it I know that the
camera is or these the screen recording is moving
so that's one other helpful thing I'm not sure if
I have any red here it doesn't look like I have
any red there so this one is just a trailer that
they're going to do the animations afterwards so
I didn't need to actually mark up the red but
I do a lot of software tutorials so if I know
that I'm going to go to a certain air area in my
software then I'll mark that as red as well green
is direction to me this is something that I do not
say but it is something that I want to just hint
at or just let myself know about something again
as I'm recording it so if I come into here most of
that is done by pauses so when I talk sometimes
I talk fast I know I've gotten that feedback
a lot they're like he was going way too fast and
that's maybe when I just get excited about things
I just kind of go and I just blend into different
sentences so when I'm doing a narration it's also
helpful for me to just pause chillax a little bit
and then go on to the next sentence there so right
here hi everyone my name is Jeff Batten welcome
to my course JavaScript and array collections
JavaScript arrays and collections pause I am
the founder and head trainer at learning Dojo
pause for a second again you can cut out those
pauses post edit to make them sound more natural
but just it lets me know that I need to just pay
attention to this not only that but there's also
the one the two and the three those are bullet
points that are going to show up so those are
different parts that I don't need to say but
I need to pause and just kind of wait for that
bullet point to come up there now this one right
here is OST now I'm going to talk about what OST
means but this is text that is going to be on the
screen but I'm not specifically going to say what
the text is because I don't need to read whatever
text is on the screen I know sometimes we tend to
read everything and the text is on the screen
so you don't necessarily need to read it and
so right here making arrays more functional and
some other Advanced methods I don't need to say
Advanced arrays they kind of get the idea there
so that is another thing those are directions
to me this is something that I need to be aware of
what's going to be on the screen but I'm not going
to say now again after I've done this a few times
seeing that green just automatically triggers that
I don't say it but I can pause for a second and
I can take a look at those directions there all
right so let's go on to the next thing so the next
one is orange now an orange is to look into the
future we're going to be talking about something
in the future we're going to be talking or you
know something that to get the person excited so
that usually helps me uh reflect a little bit more
about excitement this is something that you can
take advantage of or something like that so I'm
going to go back into here into the script so this
one right here we will be covering what you need
to know about this course that lets me know that
I need to get excited at that part so we're going
to be covering about everything you need to know
about this course and so it just helps me kind of
emphasize that a little bit more and right here
looking into the future by the end of this course
so that's something again that I can emphasize
a little bit differently so that's it for the
colors and how I mark up my script there a couple
other things that I do visually is I will also
bold important words so if I come in here you'll
notice things like Maps those are important words
sets new data collections arrays and so forth so I
am calling out those words so I can emphasize them
as I start to read them so in this case making a
raise more functional for some Advanced methods so
I'm just pausing for a second a little bit more
or I'm emphasizing the word arrays a little bit
more as well another thing you can do that kind of
works with that is bold and resize so you notice
as I go through my script here there's a couple
words that are really you know they're large
compared to the other ones because I really want
to emphasize those words in this case hi everyone
my name is Jeff bat and welcome to this course on
JavaScript arrays and collections so that helps me
emphasize really arrays and it calls out visually
on the script when I'm reading this scripts that
I need to emphasize welcome so the more I want
to emphasize it the more I'll actually resize
it as well so that's another tip and you can see
that as I go through here we have some exciting
new ways you know maybe you don't want to do
it that much we have some exciting new ways to
work with arrays and data collection a raise and
data collection are not exciting but this is if
you're if you're new or if you're familiar with
JavaScript somebody may not be familiar with how
to do a raisin collection so that's why I want
to emphasize exciting there so that is another
way to visually kind of show it and then also
typewriter text directions or screen movements
this kind of relates with the pause is I will
put that inside of typewriter text here right
here American typewriter is the text or you
could do Lucid Sans typewriter or I'll find
any typewriter text so it's like even the text
is visually different than the rest of the text
on the screen and that's more for directions
and Screen movements so even in the red so
like I mentioned this just before the upside
down question marks lets me know at the very
beginning of the sentence that it's a question
so I can make sure that I emphasize the question
right at the beginning as well highlighter head
Snappers there is something called Head Snappers
um Simon allardyce who is uh an author he's been
around for a long time lynda.com he I think he's
an author at pluralsight as well has a lot of
popular coding courses he mentions something
about head Snappers that I really like so I wanted
to make sure that that I gave him credit for that
but head Snappers is when you call the learner
back to the screen so as you're talking about a
certain item on the screen you want to draw their
attention back to you because sometimes somebody
will have the the tutorial off to the side and you
would want to say you know what you know something
that will call them back like did you know or
something that's really important or something
that you're going to emphasize that is a head
Snapper that brings them back I'm not sure if I
have any head Snappers in this one something like
here you know ecmascript was introduced to me or
was introduced so I can even highlight something
like that so that way it triggers my reading of it
as a head Snapper where I want to draw and I want
to emphasize coming back to the video and paying
attention to the video if you have a chance to
watch any of Simon allardyce videos he does this
really well so he's a great example of that of
calling it back bringing it back and saying even
questions like this where you you call back to
yourself and even anticipate different questions
like now you may be thinking or you may be
questioning or you may have a question in
your mind things like that that brings it back
and relates it back to the learner because the
learner may be thinking that and you're kind of
anticipating what they're thinking and it brings
them back it's a head Snapper it it takes them you
know looking somewhere else and bringing it back
to the screen and getting their attention back
so they're also text acronyms so you saw this on
the screen OST stands for on-screen text that is
not said so in this case we have some right here
on-screen text Advanced arrays this is not going
to be said but it's just a quick way to know that
that is on-screen text osm on-screen movements so
if you want to know exactly what's going to happen
on the screen you can put those inside of brackets
and you can trigger the on-screen or you can just
show the on-screen movements so I know exactly
what's going to happen on the screen there not
even if I'm recording the screen at the same time
I could even then move my my screen or my mouse
at that same time as I'm talking about it if you
wanted to get used to it that way as well like
I mentioned before a lot of this just comes down
to practice practicing it pulling out your iPhone
and just recording your screen recording yourself
as you read the narration and then you know over
time it gets a lot easier I've been doing the
on-screen videos for over two years but I've
been doing these different plural sites and udemy
courses for over 10 years so it's been a long time
and so I've I've picked up a lot of things but I
still have a lot of things to learn myself as well
so it's kind of an a progression it's something
that you could always improve in a certain area
maybe it's not all about the microphone but maybe
there's a better microphone that helps you or
just a better you know way to prep or breathe or
other things like that now one last thing I want
to talk about is creating lists or steps this is
what I do most commonly what I do is if I come
into my Trello when I'm prepping for a video for
example if I click on that Trello board these are
different things that I want to call out now this
is last week's video which is interactive video in
storyline so there there were a few things that I
just create little bullet point two triggers hot
spots show layers jumping back to certain points
those are certain things that I wanted to cover
in the video so as I'm recording the video I'll
have something off to the side for this video I
don't but I'll have something off to the side that
lets me know these different bullet points and so
if I'm recording something and I'm not scripting
and I forgot to cover bullet point two well I can
bring it back to bullet point two and I can make
sure that I cover that as well so that is my most
common method but the scripting and other things
have have been stuffed that I've used all the time
as well so hopefully this has been helpful for you
to at least if you're thinking about scripting if
you have some you know scripting for storyline or
or adobe Captivate or something like that and you
wanted to create the script and Mark it up this
way hopefully this has been helpful for you and
you're able to at least get one or two things
out of this as well if you like my video and
you wanted to check out more head on over to my
web say at learningdojo.ninja you can go over to
my blog posts and see all previous blog posts you
can also download different templates development
templates and articulate storyline 360 ax API
and video and you can check out full courses
everything from A to Z on articulate storyline
360. Adobe Captivate xapi fundamentals Camtasia
articulate rise custom scorm and HTML5 video
and if you like this video go ahead and go to
my YouTube channel make sure you click on that
like button and subscribe to my channel as well
and hit the Bell notification so you get notified
of all future videos as they come out that really
helps my channel allows me to keep making these
videos these free videos for you these tips and
tricks as well and comment down below what works
for you what other things that that are not in
this video that you've done when you've had to
do narration comment down below at my YouTube
video and that's it that's all I have for today
so I'll see you next time everyone [Music] foreign
[Music]